Guide to the Jonathan Lee Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Jonathan Lee papers
1781-1857
MS 958
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4.25
(10 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, notebooks, journals and sermons of Jonathan Lee, which document his professional and personal life in Massachusetts, Vermont, and Connecticut.
Lee, Jonathan, 1786-1866
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William Todd, with supplemental purchases, 1941.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Correspondence, 1781-1857. II. Sermons, 1812-1836. III. Volumes, 1804-1844.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, sermons, journals, notebooks, and other papers relating to the personal life and professional career of Jonathan Lee, a graduate of Yale University (B.A., 1809) and Congregational Minister in Otis, Massachusetts; Weybridge, Vermont; and Salisbury, Connecticut.
The Lee Papers are arranged in ten (10) boxes and total four and one-quarter (4.25) linear feet. The papers are arranged in three series: I. Correspondence, 1781-1857, II. Sermons, 1812-1836, III. Volumes, 1804-1844.
SERIES I, CORRESPONDENCE, 1781-1805, consists primarily of letters exchanged between members of the Lee family. Jonathan Lee maintained a regular correspondence with family members, including his parents, brothers, sisters, and his wife. Early letters consist of messages from Jonathan Lee to family members as he studied at Yale College and Andover Theological Seminary. Lee wrote regularly and in great detail of his studies and life at school. Lee also corresponded with family members while in the Michigan Territory during the 1820s and 1830s. He ventured there as a representative of the American Home Missionary Society, and engaged in religious work in the area of Tecumseh, Michigan. Lee exchanged religious views and family information from the Midwest, and he continued this correspondence upon his return to New England in the 1830s, after which he assumed positions in Vermont, Massachusetts, and Connecticut. During the 1840s he corresponded with his offspring quite regularly, including several letters to and from his daughter Harriet, as she recuperated from an illness in an Utica, New York asylum.
SERIES II, SERMONS, 1812-1836, consists of several handwritten sermons which Lee delivered in the course of his religious training and practice. These sermons, as indicated on the text, were often delivered several times in a variety of locations in and around New England.
SERIES III, VOLUMES, 1804-1844, consists of a commonplace book, a journal (1804-1844), and several notebooks which Lee compiled in the course of his academic work at Yale College (1808-1809).
The Lee Papers were donated by William Todd and supplemented by purchases, in 1941.
Biographical / Historical
Jonathan Lee was born on July 19, 1786, in Salisbury, Connecticut, the son of Deacon Milo and Ruth Camp Lee. He fitted for college with Rev. Ammi R, Robbins, of Norfolk, and entered the Freshman Class in Sept., 1804, but was compelled by poor health to relinquish study for an entire year during his college course. He graduated from Yale in 1809 and from Andover Theological Seminary in 1812.
Lee was ordained and installed pastor of the Congregational Church in Otis, Massachusetts in 1815. He was dismissed from this charge, July 10, 1831, at his own request. He subsequently was the pastor of the Congregational Church in Weybridge, Vermont from 1834-1837. He published an "Address, designed to be presented to a Mutual Council," called for his dismission, (pp. 23, 8°, Middlebury, Vt., 1837.) Two sermons preached at Otis were also published. In 1838 Lee returned to Salisbury to teach and resided there until his death in 1866.
He was twice married. His first wife, who died Nov. 14, 1826, was Harriet Dewey, daughter of Col. J. Danforth, of Pittsfield, Mass. He married, Nov. 25, 1827, Mary, daughter of Col. Adonijah Strong, of Salisbury. She died Dec. 24, 1863, aged 76.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Clergy -- Correspondence; Clergy -- Massachusetts; Religion; Theology; Connecticut; Michigan; Middle West; Salisbury (Conn.) -- History; Vermont; Account books; Diaries; Sermons; Clergy; Lee, Jonathan, 1786-1866; Andover Theological Seminary; Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1809; Yale University -- Students; Lee family
- Correspondence, 1781-1857; Series I; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged in chronological order.
  - 1781 - 1835 March (Box 1, Folder 1-19)
  - 1835 April - 1857 (Box 2, Folder 20-42)
  - Undated (Box 3, Folder 43-47)
- Sermons, 1812-1836; Series II; 2; (5 boxes)
  - 1812 Feb - 1817 Aug (Box 4, Folder 48-60)
  - 1817 Sep - 1820 Dec (Box 5, Folder 61-76)
  - 1821 Jan - 1824 Feb (Box 6, Folder 77-90,)
  - 1824 Mar - 1828 Feb (Box 7, Folder 91-106)
  - 1828 Mar - 1836 (Box 8, Folder 107-120)
- Volumes, 1804-1844; Series III; 1; (2 boxes)
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by record type.
  - Commonplace Book, 1809 (Box 9, Folder 121)
  - Journal, 1804-1844 (Box 9, Folder 122-125)
  - Notebooks
    - Disputes, 1808-1809 (Box 9, Folder 126-127)
    - English, undated (Box 10, Folder 128)
    - Logic, 1809 (Box 10, Folder 129)
    - Manuscript, undated (Box 10, Folder 130)
    - Philosophy, 1808 (Box 10, Folder 131)
    - Rhetoric, 1808 (Box 10, Folder 132)
    - Theology, 1809 (Box 10, Folder 133)
    - Miscellanea, undated (Box 10, Folder 134)